Daniel, um, any suggestions on which
resources you'd recommend like glancing
through as like a starting point? Like
if you I had some time before after
reading the chapter, is there like a a
good like first place to look
because there's so much resource on here
honestly. It's like
>> Yeah, that is a good question. And I
think it's more about
sort of
what what you want to get out of out of
active inference or approaching. So you
said you're a master's uh you're doing
compsai MIT. Um do you I mean most
people are not using mat lab so much
anymore but there's a nice uh
there was a nice and I'll share this in
the chat um step-by-step tutorial on
active inference put out by uh Fristen
and and and some others including Ryan
Smith. Uh, and Ryan Smith's a pretty um
has a bit of a strong reputation in the
community. Um, he does a lot with
computational psychiatry, but along the
way he's repeatedly given like tutorials
at at Yale and at Zurich and so on uh on
how to actually do this stuff because
there is at times a bit of a gap between
actually learning this versus like
knowing how to apply it in in code etc.
and getting into the models. So even if
you don't want to take the mat lab route
necessarily, it really breaks down a lot
of sort of the core maths and then along
the way you kind of get this commentary
on like sort of use cases and things
like that. So I think that's a nice
intro. Um, on the more theoretical side,
uh, active inference, a process theory,
which is a, um,
it's a bit of a long read, but it's
uh, it's it's a core text that came out
5 years before this textbook, but um,
people kind of refer back to it very
often. And it's sort of itself a a
compendium of of what Fristen and others
uh had been working on up to that point
and tries to synthesize it where I think
this textbook becomes a much stronger
kind of synthesis of the last five years
after that plus that. But uh 50 pages is
less than 200. So uh you know worth
skimming around in there. Thanks.
>> For sure.
>> Cool. Um, all right. So, thanks again
everyone for joining. I'll just I'll do
I mean this is such a short initial
chapter in this book. Uh we we're told
during this chapter like a general
rundown of what each chapter is going to
kind of be about. But the main thing is
to notice that the first half of the
book being chapters 1 through 5 versus
chapters 6 through 10 are quite
different in certain respects in that
the first half is intended to provide
more of like a formalization of active
inference. get a lot of the core uh
ideas and the theory and the framework
across and it does quite quickly by
chapter two we start getting into the
maths especially looking at uh baze uh
bases rule or basis theorem and getting
into kind of like a basian framework and
thinking about uh also probability
distributions
but nonetheless it's still it's still
very kind of prosaic relative to the
second half of the textbook which is
where uh it it much more strongly
discusses particular models uh mainly
exemplar models that are used in active
inference. It refers to uh published
research up to that point to kind of
give uh more expansive explanations of
these different models. Uh not just to
get you familiar with what's already
been done, but to kind of break down
their architectures and and kind of
cases of of what they were used to study
uh in order to provide you with sort of
fodder or information on how you might
construct your own model. even if you're
trying to do something more novel, uh
there are many kind of components and
and core concepts to be taken away from
the second half of the book. Um but all
of that being said, uh we'll I'll I'll
talk about some of the core ideas that
we're already introduced to in this
first chapter. Um we know that that
active inference is a normative
framework. They they describe uh this
sort of neats versus scruffy's debate.
Uh I was not familiar with that kind of
debate until I read this book, but I it
it it clicked and and it's what I find
very often in social sciences where
people are much more contentious uh sort
of with one another and there's so many
different angles to to approach
different phenomena. Um but in any case
it's to uh it mainly approaches um
concepts of perception and action which
we're quite familiar with those who who
study neuroscience especially perception
uh sometimes action is kind of treated
separately or or there are different
kinds of models that might be used or or
or different like uh augmentations of
perception models to look at decision
making. But but it can boil down for
some to just perception. Um for active
inference it's both. So active inference
aims to um um kind of overcome this sort
of classical or traditional notion of
taking the brain or the organism or the
entity as a passive observer of sensory
information. uh rather there's
perception in that sense but there's
also action in that uh you know we as
humans or or or or cellular organisms or
entire cultures uh will will uh act in
order to realize their goals or to seek
information which are two very important
kind of notions in that that more
clearly uh are comprehensible whenever
you start to get the the maths of how
they break that down but for the time
being it's to recognize we have
perception and action and then with
action we have this kind of subdivision
into information seeking and and goal
directed behavior which work together
and and can quote unquote naturally
balance one another. So um for those who
are familiar with sort of um kind of the
machine learning reinforcement learning
paradigms like with reinforcement
learning there's frequently uh you know
there there will be kind of these rules
applied to say what what does it mean to
have exploratory behavior versus goal
directed behavior. Um, free energy
minimization involves kind of like a
so-called natural way of of balancing
that or determining what those things
are as opposed to forcing some kind of
stochastic rule that says like, oh, 5%
of the time do something random so you
don't get caught in a a local minima.
Um,
>> can I ask a question about that?
Actually, I I had that on my notes. Um,
>> yeah. Yeah, go for it. I I also have
feel like I've had that dissatisfaction
with reinforcement learning about like
if it feeling like a hacky way of of
trying to put in exploration. Um but
then so later on the chapter um I think
there was something very similar to what
you said about essentially that that
balance of exploration exploitation like
in some sense naturally falls out of
this um when you when you are thinking
about planning. Um but then with the way
the chapter opens and also the way you
just described it, it kind of sounded to
me like it was sort of just like
declared um that that those are two the
two goals that are being pursued by
action. Like on the one hand it's like
you know getting sense data that
corresponds with goals, the other hand
getting information which feels a little
bit like like building it in by design.
Not that that's not that there's
anything like inherently wrong with
that, but I guess I was um wasn't didn't
feel like I was clear on like is that
something that like naturally falls out
or is that something that's kind of
built in the way?
>> That's a I I see like like the the
difference between like naturally
falling out versus like being built in.
So
I would
it might be a little bit early to get to
this given it's chapter one but um
so this is uh this these are the various
breakdowns of what's called expected
free energy. Uh that and variational
free energy are kind of the core
quantities here. And the only reason why
there there's a a division between those
two, why we have two different free
energy minimization rules um instead of
one is that this is sort of expected
free energy is sort of the free energy
of the future uh which is a bit
different and we there there are
organisms who do not necessarily even
have capacities like the kind of you
know neurobiological capacities or
otherwise to plan. um you know very
cellular organisms like tend to lack
this and they're a bit more reactive to
their immediate environment. Uh but in
any case for those who who do have that
capacity um it can be broken down. We
we'll ignore you know uh the vast
majority of this equation but just for
the starting line we have information
gain and then we have pragmatic value
and uh information gain would kind of be
the equivalent of like seeking
information. Uh whereas pragmatic value
would be more in line with kind of how
you stated the the goal- directedness
that is like bringing expected
observations or observations you want to
see uh you know in line with with
reality or the other way around acting
in order to realize what you want to see
right so given that this is kind of
scored over what policy to take what
action to take what sequence of actions
to take it's kind of like saying for
each action you get you you get both of
these, right? Um, so, so I guess we
could say it's sort of built in in the
sense of like, well, you know, if we
define expected free energy this way,
then this is one way that that can kind
of be uh um the terms can kind of be
assembled such that that this is what
they look like and that's what they
equate to. Um, I'm still working on my
ability to kind of use like everyday
examples of how to describe these
things, right? So it's like information
gain would be like let's start with
pragmatic value. I'm hungry. I eat some
food. Um great you know that that was
pragmatic value by eating the food. Uh
information gain. I'm hungry. Uh I need
to find food. I need to locate where it
is at. That's not immediately uh
accomplishing my goal, but it is on the
path there. It minimizes my uncertainty
about the world around me and how to
accomplish the goal. And so all of these
different policies or actions uh are
assumed to have their their be scored by
expected free energy. Um and so both of
those terms are there. So there's no
like epsilon greedy like rule here going
on. Uh it's it's like this is how the
maths play out. And in terms of like
code, it's like just infer policies like
run a line and that's this is what you
you end up with. Um a and like given
that there's some here who have already
read the textbook, some of this will
already look familiar then. And so it's
kind of like the this C matrix uh which
COD is annoyingly kind of putting the
pencil over, but the the C is something
like preferences or like having goals.
It's a it's a in this case for a
discrete state space setting it's a
distribution probability distribution
over different potential observations
you know uh
being uh I I observe my stomach is
growling versus it's not it's actually
sad and feels good I'm I'm full uh you
know higher probability for the latter
because that's what I want like that's a
very simplistic simplified example um
and so the y tilda would be oh what do I
expect do I expect that that uh by doing
this action I will elicit a new
observation that is I'm sated I'm good
uh right so if if this is very high
noting that this is a negative term then
we are by by increasing the pragmatic
value we're we're reducing this overall
quantity right um with information gain
of course looks a little bit more
complex if good old um Colbeck Leebler
divergence which is just kind of it's an
equation that essentially just kind of
measures the difference between two
different distributions. Uh this first
one is uh what do I think's going on in
the world X conditioned on the actual
observations sensory observations I
received Y and pi the action I took
versus just what do I think is going on
in the world given uh the action I took.
So it's kind of like we want to be able
to do things and and and they link up
with with the world. And so when we
engage in action, we do things in order
to change uh hidden states of the world.
I my stomach growling is a sensory
observation. My idea that I'm hungry or
not hungry would be a hidden state in
this case, right? There's no there's no
sense I I have to relate things. So
that's perception. Um but once I take in
new data, what actually happened now?
Right? So this is it's a form of
updating one's beliefs between what what
what is it that I think my actions do to
change the world given the new data I
received so that I can update things
relative to just what do I think
regardless of the sensory observation
I'm receiving if I do something what how
will the nature of the world change. So
it's it's information gain is kind of
just like taking actions to elicit
observations the why uh and figure out
did you learn anything new. If we
increase that once again that's a
negative term and so we end up reducing
um expected free energy as well. So
>> thanks Andrea looks like Muhammad has
his hand up.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Go for it. Um
>> yeah I think I don't know like we maybe
jumping quite ahead but I was just
curious about since we've gotten to the
reinforcement learning part here uh like
does like the whole framework of active
inference actually posit how do you even
construct the state space in the first
place like how do you even discretize
your whole continuous space like since
you're tracking probabilities like you
can't track it onto everything you have
to discretise your your whole world
around you does it actually posit how
you do that process or or we're just
assuming okay given this state space how
should the model update its
probabilities over these possibilities.
Um so yeah I'm just curious about if we
have any ideas of in this framework that
how do you even decide how do you
construct that state space in the first
place?
>> Yeah know that that that is a great
question. Um and
so so first like and for those who like
read the textbook or we'll keep going
with it like we'll they'll notice that
chapter 7 and chapter 8 are about models
but in very different settings. Chapter
7 being about discrete state spaces and
then chapter 8 being about continuous.
And so it's like we we already like have
this kind of division between how to
look at a state space construction in
the first place uh and and making a
choice between the two uh with the
continuous state spaces. That's where
like the phrase predictive coding has
come up frequently uh already during
this this meeting and some folks have
brought that up. that is going to be
much more aligned with the notion of
like continuous models versus discrete
state spaces where a lot of these
equations
um describe both um there's another
paper I I should probably actually um
share with you all for anyone who's
interested but there is a um and this is
Ryan Smith again but there's a there's a
nice paper that he put out last year um
on the status of predictive coding
meaning uh the empirical status of of
predictive coding. And the whole sense
of that is you know um unlike a kind of
cultish
uh you know take that this is more of a
like well these models need to be fit to
empirical data. They need to be
validated. They should be benchmarked
versus you know other standard models
that are that are comparable but
nonetheless you don't necessarily assume
free energy minimization etc. Um, and
it's he so he covers a lot of this in a
really nice kind of succinct way. And uh
um
all that said um one free energy does
kind of play out similarly in each of
these models is just the equation for
how you handle the state space. Um, but
it's it's not what I mean to say is just
because a model is continuous and
another model is discreet, it doesn't
necessarily mean that they are like
intrinsically
entirely different aside from how you're
you're you're kind of dividing up the
state space. Um then another kind of
answer to the question in terms of what
choices to and and another bit which is
um the idea of having like hybrid models
where you have like for example a common
construction that comes up again way
later in the textbook but um having like
a kind of lower level model that takes
in like s continuous sensory
observations
um you know just sensory receptors etc
which tend to you know typically we
empirically we we measure those or or
even record those and more continuous
spaces those might be received by a
lower level continuous model but then
through inference be linked up to a
higher order discrete state space model.
So you imagine like making like a trying
to model a I don't know a mouse in a
T-mas is a is a frequent example that's
actually carried out in in laboratories
and so on. And it's like, well, the
mouse, you know, encounters a continuous
world that it's within and continuous
observations in it. Yet, it must make a
discrete choice about should I go left
or right in his teammates in order to
get a discrete reward that is like, you
know, some kind of cheese or or or or
uh something sweet uh that's in one arm
of the maze. So, th those kinds of
structures are very much possible and
employed. Um I've been playing around
with them myself recently. Now and then
finally another question is like what is
the particular phenomena of interest
that you have and what decision should
you make in order to confront that using
uh a generative model and making what
kinds of uh architectural decisions to
to actually approach that system of
interest. Um so if you're you know if
you're working with neuroiming data
which tends to be viewed as continuous
data even though there are like sampling
rates and it some minute level actually
it's quite discreet and could be
represented as like know individual uh
rows in a in a in a matrix or
spreadsheet structure but but
nonetheless we we tend to analyze it as
continuous um you know so chapter six
gets into a lot of that before it gets
deep into the models it's sort recipe
for active inference describing like
well you do you do have to make various
decisions right like you have to make
various decisions on like what should
the state's face look like and and and
how how should we construct that what
makes sense here relative to the
literature that's already been
published. So, so in that sense, it's
not trying to claim that there's any
kind of like magical, you know,
oneandone approach to modeling really
anything. And anyone who does
computational modeling, whether they're
into active inference or not, it it
knows this and is going to have to
confront that question, right? I mean,
if we if we use uh linear regression to
try and describe the relationship
between X and Y, we're making an
assumption of, you know, linearity is a
valid way of describing the relationship
between these things. And if you
disagree with that then suddenly you
disagree with the entirety of the model.
Right? So so at some level you do still
confront that fundamental question. And
then ideally if you're working in a more
empirical setting where you could fit it
to data it's there that you know fingers
crossed there's more validity to be
found in your model beyond just you know
hoping it works out.
Um like actually Daniel has like some
interesting like comments in the chat
and like I want to take if you can like
elaborate more on that like so I'm
thinking in the perspective of like
since active inference makes claims
about what cognitive agents are doing
like so you're coming at it like using
active inference to model cognitive
phenomena. I'm just thinking it makes
normative claims of what cognitive
agents themselves are doing. So I was
curious about whether it can describe
how cognitive agents themselves decide
in which state space to use or maybe
those are questions beyond that
framework.
This this is one of the kind of core
um strange attractors is like map
territory. I'll put some more map
territory related discussions but I take
a very strongly instrumental take like
active inference the framework can't say
anything about cars or planes or birds
because it's a human created construct
which can be applied by cognitive agents
to make claims about systems.
So the idea that the framework sort of
like generically or unilaterally or
already makes an opinionated claim about
what a system it's like saying what what
do linear regressions say about the
relationship between this and that. It's
like surely we don't want linear
regression framework to be opinionated
on such a kind of last mile problem and
it's not. But you could use linear
regression in a specific investigation
to have datadriven claims about how this
and that are associated. So
again open to everyone's take obviously
but active inference does not make
claims period. It doesn't speak. People
use active inference and hide behind
apparatuses of theories to make it sound
like well science says this or
reinforcement learning says this would
happen. It's like instead of just saying
I am using reinforcement learning to say
this happens. So that's kind of a
grammatical thing, but actually it
becomes really important because it's
like is someone trying to bring the
hammer of a whole framework down or like
act like the framework is already giving
opinionated stances and then it's like
well then you can model different
possibilities like if you say I'm
modeling choice behavior in this mouse
do these data better fit with a two or
three state discrete model
and then you're having a datadriven
discussion about like what is the
relative evidence for a two-choice model
or three- choice model and how much does
the increase in fit merit being
penalized by adding more parameters.
That's like the basian information
criterion. So there are a lot of really
nuanced ways to pursue structure
learning and inference
but none of them involve the framework
speaking for itself somehow.
And the first step in seeing that is
just realizing that generative models
are constructed artifacts.
But it's not like well what is what does
active inference say about dyslexia
is is is essentially a category error
question.
Let me maybe rephrase myself there I
guess. Um so like if you just want to
say instrumentally like okay uh active
inference instrumentally tells us how we
should be designing our generative
models about and how we want to capture
model how we want to model cognitive
phenomena and so if we want to model
like we do structural learning right we
make abstractions and if I want to model
that phenomenon itself
is this the right tool to use or like it
offers us nothing on that perspective.
Do you get my point? Like maybe that
might be a more instrumental question.
And so I'm just curious guy going into
this because like I'm uh I coming on
onto this idea of like uh if I want to
let's say automate science itself like
intriguing there's like a whole group
like like this machine learning for
science right like uh how do you make
machine learning and techniques of doing
science itself and you know it's right
now a crazy idea in my mind but like
I've been thinking about you know how
humans really make abstractions and you
know deal with like reality and break it
down and so I'm like thinking okay like
we do this cognitive phenomena of
science like how do you capture that how
do you model that itself and so that's
why I was like thinking does this whole
active inference framework tells us
something about modeling or capturing
that phenomena and maybe that's more of
an instrumental question and yeah I
might be asking questions that are not
really relevant to chapter one but just
curious about what you guys think about
it
>> if all you have is reward you're always
going to need to to make a reward
function
somehow cover information gain. So if
you want to model epistemic ecosystems
that have goal seeking and
open-endedness,
then it's a natural framework. And I'll
put some resources about like some of
those like kind of science meta-cience
active inference approaches, but a lot
of them are are not executable code.
>> Okay. that would be still useful for me
to look at.
>> I have a couple of more basic questions,
but I didn't want to uh derail your
presentation here, Andrew. I don't know
if you should we save questions until
the end.
>> No, no worries at all. I'll um I'm just
kind of like gathering together the the
thoughts because the whole thing is that
chapter one is always interesting
because it's like oh this is interesting
but also like we're quickly introduced
to a lot of terms that won't be expanded
upon till later in the textbook. So I'm
not incredibly surprised that like
here's me pulling up like an equation
that appears four chapters from now and
a second ago we had the kind of meta
discussion of of choosing how to
construct your model. I'm like, "Oh,
yeah. Chapter nine has a good
explanation of a of sort of these
particular author's take on on, you
know, there's there's constructing a
model and then there's like the the fact
that we are the mo as the modelers have
our own understanding of that model.
Like whenever we're doing the the model
fitting process where we have data,
we're trying to put together a model and
we're making our own inferences about
what the model should be to represent
the the supposed model that the the the
mouse in the T-maze is equipped with. Uh
you know, so it's it's it just you know,
infinite regress sometimes for for
modelers. But um yeah like I I'll say as
a as a basis for this chapter we are
told that the the way the framework is
set up is to uh assume that that it's
interesting because it takes different
kinds of sort of agnostic approaches to
some things. uh for example, generative
models, right? Like this book does not
make a strong stance on saying that you
that that you know a person has an
explicit generative model or if it's
such that the inference processes
occurring in the brain are as if it has
a generative model, right? Like there's
no magical idea that we can go into the
brain and pull out like this is exactly
what the state space looks like, etc.,
etc.
um as far as the sort of optimization
function goes and free energy
minimization it's there that it's it's
really mainly there that that Fristen
and um a great researcher Isura and some
others are doing the empirical work of
like actually you know working on
validating the free energy principle and
then from there it's like well if if if
that's a kind of process or process
theory that that we're willing to at
least entertain then it's from there
that we can start to entertain these
models that utilize that kind of um
optimization function. So um so we know
from this chapter that we're kind of
looking at a basian framework and in
simple terms which it'll get more into
it in chapter 2 but for those unfamiliar
with that uh the general idea of like
you you you have beliefs you receive new
information you might use that
information to update your beliefs right
so like uh I think that this coin in my
hand is a fair coin probability ility.5
heads,.5 tails. Um, and so I might flip
the coin 100 times, realize like, oh,
isn't it bizarre that 99 times out of a
100 it landed on heads, and the one time
it landed on tails, I kind of like moved
kind of funny and and it hit the wall or
something and it just happened to fall
on tails. I suddenly infer like, oh, I
don't actually think anymore that this
is a fair coin, right? It almost always
lands on heads, right? So from there I
might update my beliefs. This is not a
fair coin. So I received new and sensory
information from observing the coin in
order to make a new you know inference.
Like um the idea of this coin being a
fair coin or a biased coin is already a
way of splicing things out saying oh
those are two discrete possibilities for
this coin. Another way of looking at it
is I might even try and estimate based
upon those numbers of values what the
bias of the coin is. So now we're in a
slightly more continuous space, right?
Like is the is the bias point, you know,
instead of it being 0.5, it's like
0.99.01.
That starts to look a little bit more
like a frequentist uh paradigm if I
break it down to that level. But
nonetheless, receive information, update
your beliefs. We're given some other uh
terms. I've already mentioned perception
and action. Uh so we have learning which
is is similar to inference but it would
be actually adjusting model parameters.
Um that means like my beliefs about this
coin it's 0.5 heads.5 tails. Um but I
might over time adjust my belief my the
very thing that I use to make inferences
about this coin. I decide oh this is a
biased coin. Now whenever I flip it I'm
not going to expect 0.5 versus.5. I'm
going to expect 0.99 versus 01
dramatically different. If I hold on to
that, that's a new categorical
probability distribution that informs me
of what to expect from this coin and I I
change that. That means I've changed my
generative model. I've changed the
parame outcome. Right? So to learn over
time in more simple terms is to actually
adapt to changing circumstances. not
just react to them with the same model
but actually changing the model itself
the parameters within it. There's
another aspect called structure learning
which would be actually an actual change
in the model like you add a new SPL a
new slot in the categorical probability
distribution or you remove one uh you
know using some kind of information
criteria. Um so so those are different
notions in there. Chapter for those who
are most interested in kind of the
neuroscientific aspects of this
neurobiological it's chapter five where
you'll see a lot about message passing
which is some of the most I mean those
are the densest pieces of the maths
here. Um but it it's there that we
finally get discussions of like
superficial versus deep pyramidal cells
um interconnectivity between different
neuronal populations. The idea of them
passing messages between one another
where you tend to have these kinds of
hierarchal processes where there are
these down like a downward past
predictions coming from the brain and
and uh uh rising uh prediction errors.
they're actually being matched against
incoming sensory observation. So it's
like you have your beliefs about the
world but you through sensory
observation like start to realize
there's contra uh contradictory
information right and so it's from there
that we start to update our beliefs like
it it gets much more into sort of the
the the more concrete like roots of of
where this comes from and a lot of the
work that that uh that that Friston's
been doing the past several decades uh
at this point with working on neuroiming
data and then trying to formalize that
into a scheme that could then be
represented in a single chapter in a
textbook. So it's quite dense. Uh but
yeah, so um there there there's a lot
more to this textbook and that we we
frequently have folks who who join who
are not exactly like excited to learn
the maths but are more interested in the
conceptual aspects. So I'm just trying
to like get some of these words out
here. I I know that I'm getting a little
dense with with some of them because I
kind of am trying to make my own in
inferences about the interests of this
group. But um yeah, it's uh I I do want
to give a second to voice for anyone who
hasn't had the opportunity to speak yet.
Uh like if they have any kind of
questions or anything they got out of
this and and or or or if they want to
chat about about something because it
would be informative for me going
forward of maybe what kind of things we
could focus on for next time. Um, yeah,
if anyone has any thoughts,
I have a question for you. um regarding
how is this um you know both free energy
principle and active inference has been
used in studying causal inference or say
something like potential outcomes
framework and things like that.
>> Has there been studies or has there been
papers that you can suggest that have
looked into cause and effect and use of
active inference? In other words, how do
organisms can alter their environment
and get and act on their immediate
environment
in in in in terms of
uh causality?
>> That's a good I mean because I I have my
own personal interests in causal. I mean
it this is and I I'm maybe it's just
given the amount of time we ha we have
left but so this might not be a
satisfactory answer to that question
because I don't I don't have any papers
immediately that like are explicitly
focused on active inference and causal
inference but I will say uh as far as
the general idea of doing something like
um
so from my background we we do agent
based modeling is a kind of
computational paradigm which is you know
but but this is done in in cancer
research. You know this is done in in
many different areas. And so the idea of
like simulating computationally modeling
some kind of entity or multiple entities
within an environment where they uh you
know may interact with that environment.
they receive inputs, they release
outputs, they receive obser some kind of
observations, they they elicit some kind
of actions back out into the
environment. Um if if if we want to just
take a kind of a for now like a softer
approach to looking at causal inference
and saying like oh well if if we track
all of this over time by running it
playing it out in terms of a simulation
>> to where we can track which which which
internal variables matter in these
models that are leading to particular of
emergent behaviors
>> um and then looking at how those
emergent behaviors then impact the
environment. So, so there's a lot of
kind of like um near simultaneity
uh in looking at these things as kind of
like an action perception loop. Uh when
you model them, you do play them out
over time. So you could, you know, in a
toy example with a mouse and a
teammates, you could run that for 60
trials, three time steps per trial in a
discrete time setting. Um but so so you
see that the idea is to model dynamics
that play out over time and so
necessarily there would have to be some
kind of causality there. Um like in the
sense that you know it's it's by the
agent doing this particular action at
this particular time that leads to this
particular outcome in the environment
which then leads to you know some kind
of response from the environment. So um
so so all in all I would say yes like
the the the quick that the the shortest
answer is like yes like a lot of people
are trying to use these kinds of models
like almost expressly to understand the
dynamics and that would entail some kind
of like causality. Um I mean there there
are those who like include things like
stochasticity
and assumptions that you know what what
happens whenever you're in environment
that doesn't have like onetoone direct
like deterministic rules.
>> Um and then they try to see how agents
might adapt to that kind of
stochcasticity. Um or or maybe like they
the the agents adapt to the amount that
is deterministic but never becoming so
precise that the the agent assumes it's
in a a perfectly uh deterministic
um environment if that makes sense. So,
so yeah, there
>> it does. And I think when you were
speaking um Daniel um suggested a paper
published in nature about the dynamic
causal modeling of uh COVID 19 and I
think that was a very good um you know
it's a good example almost like a you
know telltale example of what you were
talking here in this particular
situation. The other thing that
interests me though is if you think in
terms of the potential outcomes
framework that what if
yeah X were not to happen
um you know what would be the change in
the um in the state of Y. So if assuming
that say X leads to Y then we say not X
would be not Y right?
So that's a causal premise.
So the probability of
Y given X yeah is what we get to see
right. So if the if the X states were
going to be changed Y would not occur.
It seems to me that when we talk in
terms of active inference,
that underlying fundamental causal
thinking still goes on in how an
organism or how an entity kind of
determines its position with respect to
the sensory or you know otherwise
environmental cues that that that
organism is getting or that agent is
receiving here. So my question was
around that and um you know you've
touched on what what we we were
basically meaning.
>> Yeah.
>> It's just I was wondering if somebody
has done a formal mathematical modeling
of the potential outcomes framework
using the active inference
>> theory.
>> Yeah. No, absolutely. I mean I I think
that every model that I've seen thus far
that expressly is like an active
inference model and that's the the
framework and approach that people are
taking usually what they're doing when
they construct these models is to not
just construct them in one way and and
say deterministically like this is how
this works but they will play around
with the parameters and run them with
different kinds of benchmarks not just
for the sake of like oh I'm trying to
make you know an extremely amazing
predictive model but rather like if
they're trying to simulate empirical
phenomena then yeah that's exactly what
they're trying to do like entertaining
counterfactuals what would happen if
things went this way instead or we had
these kind of parameters at the start or
these conditions or otherwise I'm
personally very interested in things
like that I've written a um I presented
at a University of Pennsylvania with
computational social scientists I gave
like a three-hour talk on like multi-
aent simulations where you have agents
learning with one another and say like
if you have these this kind of network
structure between the agents, then we
tend to see these kinds of emerging
behaviors as opposed to these with these
kinds of network structures and and so
so yeah, I mean it's it's those kinds of
questions would definitely be
interesting to a lot of folks who are in
active inference and vice versa.
>> On on that note, Andrew, um would you be
kindly u able to share that uh copy of
the of that uh presentation that you
gave if you have one? uh if you have a
copy of that as well. I'll tell you why
I'm asking you this is because at the
moment I've got a PhD student who's
looking at um systems thinking and uh
you know systems modeling of um people
accessing uh health services uh of those
people who have got um you know
postacute covid syndrome and how what
kind of um you know health service
organizations are working and she's
taking on a systems thinking approach to
it and when I was listening to your um
you know conversation I was wondering
that this kind of thinking would really
benefit um the student to look into
these you know uh I mean some of the
things that you're talking about and we
can have a discussion around that so if
you can kindly you know provide that be
excellent
>> no absolutely um um I'd be happy to do
that I I put into the chat this is uh
it's a bit messy but but one of my
GitHub repositories that has kind of a
collection of just a couple of the talks
I've given but also O has some code and
more importantly it has this this
slideshow presentation that is kind of a
intro to active inference and it has
various links. Um, I'll be honest, I've
been so busy over the past year that
like the the the work I've done deserves
to just be a paper and I should work on
publishing, but I've had no time. Uh,
unfortunately, so it's not the cleanest,
but but I would share that that link
with with them and and um um let them
have a look if there's anything of of
interest. Yeah, for sure. Um because
that's what I was trying to teach. I
mean with with computational social
science we're already doing the
agent-based modeling active influence
would not be a dramatic revolution
rather it would just be aligning it much
more thoroughly with work that's being
done uh in in decisionm and inoscience
that goes beyond some of the kind of
minimalist assumptions that are made
about human behavior. Uh it's sort of
like instead of thinking of like profit
maximization for an economist like maybe
think of free energy minimization like
we do more seeking a monetary value.
Yes.
>> Uh right. And and yet in terms of like
computational tractability you know not
every student who does these things has
an entire data center available to
themselves. Well this is why there's
been a lot of simplicity in agentbased
modeling for so many years right. It's
it's a it's a empirical problem of us
not having the the technology that we
need to really run some kind of massive
large scale computation. And that's
something that's very attractive about
the free energy principle, right? Like
in so far as like it's been uh
empirically validated at at particular
levels in the particular experiments
that that have been carried out to to
test for that. Um like it it it's still
a tractable problem. It's it's you're
still ultimately looking at one major
quantity or perhaps two if you're
looking at planning and expected energy,
but still not not too much more than
that. Uh right. So so replace the dollar
sign with something that is is is much
more thoroughly kind of, you know,
thought through and and and kind of
bears in in other areas of literature,
right? beyond just the silo of just you
know economics or something like that.
>> Exactly. And that's I think is the
biggest attractiveness of uh of of of an
approach here. Anyway, I'll let uh you
know John continue with his uh
observations and thank you everyone
because while we were having this
conversation uh Abas and uh you know um
and Daniel both of you u put up some
excellent resources that I'm looking at
and you help John
>> um and briefly because we we are
unfortunately out of time that kind of
flew by in some respects but I was Just
looking at uh
Rachel's comments uh applying these
principles to computation modeling your
own models model revision computational
psychiatry. Yeah, cool.
>> We have a lot of overlap I think and I
figured it would be easier for me to
just share a link uh versus trying to
explain.
>> Yeah. No, cool. It's uh
neurocomputational approaches and neuro
neuropenomenology. That's I'm currently
working with
I'm working with a team where it's it's
very expressly like kind of like a
working with a team includes a clinical
therapist as well as someone who kind of
does like behavioral research uh
regarding like avoidance and uh and so
we've been working on this problem uh
this project for for trying to model uh
certain dynamics uh that they're
commonly found in the symptomat
PTSD. Um, and so
>> I saw that listed in your projects. I
would be interested in hearing more. Um,
but yeah, in general, anything that you
want to link back to your work with
neuro imaging or general uh behavioral
studies would be interesting.
>> Yeah. No, that that's great. And there's
a lot of so there's been a lot of
literature on these on these things. Um
what one issue I frequently find is that
people are repeatedly trying to do
discrete state spaceon
uh kind of theoretical model.
>> Um I like Ryan Smith's work that I that
I referenced earlier in the chat um
because he kind of covers all the
grounds, right? So and he you know he
has a lab and so he's carried out
experiments where he fits these active
inference models to to empirical data.
So, I would definitely like kind of
point to him as a quick reference.
>> Yeah, that that's like my main question
at this point is like is anyone actually
using this or are we just are we still
just talking about the possibility? And
it seems like maybe we're at that
turning point. Um
>> yeah,
>> but yeah, that's vibes
>> for sure. And it's uh there's a good it
it has a funny title just because it's
like slightly funny, but it it's called
Gut Inference. Uh and I'll share that.
Um, and that is a study that uh Ryan's
been playing out for some time and some
of his studies he'll like repeat them or
he'll do them with the same participants
a whole year later. So I just I
appreciate the depth to which he goes to
like focus on the actual model fitting
and and validation. But with this paper,
it's just like um this is kind of
studying reaction times and things like
that, but still it's it's drawing from
multiple forms of data. And um I just I
think it's without going into a lot of
detail, I think it's a nice example of
some of the work he's done. Um yeah and
then and then sticking to the textbook
um a lot of the predictive if you see
the phrase predictive coding or if you
look at like chapter 8 where it talks
more about continuous models those are
the things that will more directly be
applied to neuroiming
not just neuroiming data but but given
like the the speed at which it's
collected is continuous data like those
are probably sort of the exemplars for
how to get started on thinking of of how
to apply this to to that data. So, um,
>> got it. Thanks a lot.
>> Yeah, for sure. Um, and then I think
we're just about out of time, but John,
did you did you want to throw something
out there? I said a very basic um
terminology question and is I assume
this will come up again later but um is
it's the first time when he's
introducing or the book is introducing
um kind of the what B optimal you know
active inference requires they it talks
about minimizing highs and then later on
the chapter as talking about the if the
brain's doing anything it must be
minimizing free energy
>> um
>> and I'm I'm kind of noticing those like
I don't think it's free energyy's
technically been defined yet. Um
I think it was loosely listed as like a
proxy for surprise. Is that is that an
appropriate way of understanding what's
are those terms interchangeable in the
sense that free energy is a is a is a
you know approximate measure of
surprise? That just seems like a very
core uh piece of what's going on here.
>> No, for sure. That's a that's a very
good question and uh I'm I'm like
looking for it right now but somewhere
later in the book they actually like
provide this like simplified table. Um
page 50 I I won't go too much into it
but for now like your intuition is
correct. It is kind of like a proxy.
However, they're definitely like not
necessarily equal. Um if only they were.
Uh so so surprise basian surprise the
issue with trying to directly compute
that as a quantity is that it's
frequently intractable. Um it doesn't
allow for like marginalization
in all cases. And so what what happen
essentially what's happening is that
like you know if I want to go down the
street to get a drink from a convenience
store I don't necessarily have to think
about the spatial layout of the opposite
side of the world. Like I don't have to
think necessarily about everything that
I could possibly think about in order to
optimize. Right? So that that's a crude
way of saying that, but but it it's it's
so
free energy minimization involves like
variational inference and it involves
certain kinds of rules and and for
marginalizing over probability like
state spaces and so um free energy is a
tractable proxy for basian surprise. And
so
>> if you can minimize that quantity as
much as possible, you would necessarily
be minimizing surprise, you just might
not be getting it down to um as low as
possible. So free energy in this case is
actually it's like an upper bound on
surprise, right? So if you can bring
that down and and then whenever you
actually break open those equations that
I was sharing on the screen earlier um
like if you can minimize your KL
divergence as much as possible to where
it's virtually zero it's in that case
that basine surprise would necessarily
equate to free energy right so it's like
you can get close to actually minimizing
surprise itself but if your KL term is
still greater than zero then you're
still just looking at like a proxy. Um,
I hope that wasn't too deep, but maybe
that gets across. Yeah.
>> And the surprise here is the surprise
between the discrepancy between your
preferred state of the world and your
actual observations, not between your
expected state of the world and and or
pred not between your predictions and
observations, but between your
preferences or your goals and
observations. That's at least that's you
introduce it in uh you're on whatever
page this is 1.4.1 4.1
the discrepancy between your preferred
state which is seemed to me not how I
would have traditionally thought of that
but
>> yeah no also a good point that you
brought up and uh like for sake of time
how to think of so with I mentioned
earlier there's variational free energy
and then there's expected free energy um
actually with variational free energy
that would involve just what you expect
not necessarily what you want so to
speak uh for those interested in like
dynamic chemical systems and thinking
about like attractors like the notion of
an attractor. You can think of
preferences in expected free energy like
what what you want so to speak. Uh what
you can think of them kind of like a
reward distribution in a sense. It's
like oh a point8 for the cheese in the
versus like you know an aversive
stimulus in the other arm of the teams
would be a 2. like that you can look at
that those as expectations but that are
acting as attractors that are actually
attracting the agent towards them. Um I
don't know if I'm doing the best job in
describing it but it's it's kind of like
it's both. It's both of the things you
said. It's variational free energy
relate will relate to what you expect
regardless of what you actually want in
that instance. Then expected free energy
is about how do you score what you
should do in order to get to your
preferences? Not just what you expect,
but like your your preferences. They
kind of get equated in that sense. So um
with variational free energy, it's like
that could that could change like what
you like what you expect from the world
around you could change over time
through learning or otherwise.
Meanwhile, my blood oxygen regulation in
my body needs to be in a certain range
otherwise my I'm going to dissipate,
right? Like that would be an equivalent
for something like preferences that you
could think in like a hardline
homeostatic seeking kind of way is like
I need to have so much so much oxygen
and glutamate and so on in my body
otherwise I'm I'm done for. Right? So
that it's through expected free energy
that I figure out like, oh, I need to go
eat some food in order to fulfill these
preferences. So preferences aren't a
flimsy like do I want chocolate or
vanilla. They they like in thinking
about them, you can also think about
them as like how does a an organism stay
alive and maintain its its well-being.
So that that's the significance of
preferences. Um, I would say just look a
little bit more about uh the equations
for variational free energy and expected
free energy and you'll just you'll see a
lot more of that just literally in the
next chapter and then chapter four we'll
kind of bring it back around too. So
>> yeah, I I'm assuming we'll come back to
that. I I'll just pin that because I
don't want to I know we're over time,
but I do want to that's one of the
things I want to get ironed out to be
clear. I still
>> It's a good Yeah, it's a good question
because it's like if you only ever
expected what you wanted, right? Then
it's like how would you actually be able
to account for what actually tends to
happen, right? Um you
delusions, I guess. Uh so yeah, we we
can get more into that though. But this
was a good session. So thank you all
again for for attending and uh look
forward to hopefully seeing you next
week. Uh next week it will uh well maybe
not next week for you all for the
evening session. The evening session
next week we'll be doing chapter six for
the other cohort. Again it's it gets a
little confusing. Feel free to email uh
Daniel or I or the the main uh institute
email address. It's on the on the site.
And uh yeah, thank you all so much.
>> Two weeks from now, right, was when
we'll do the next
>> Okay.
>> Exactly. And I'm sure this is
>> I'm sure this is clarified in the
documentation, but is there like a chat
that we can all discuss ideas over the
next two weeks asynchronously?
>> Yeah. Yeah, for sure.
>> And if that's in the docs, just tell me
to go look at the docs. Happy to do
that. Yeah, I think I think uh whenever
uh I think it's Daniel who sends out the
the emails for the the textbook group.
Um he should have included any kind of
like rel like significant links in
there. Um two two quick things are like
one there's a discord channel there all
kinds of folks in there who are you know
approaching different things. So you
know uh engage with that as you like and
then and then there are more general
channels for discussing things but then
there's also the textbook group on the
KOD where you can kind of get into like
more direct questions about the
textbooks.
>> Oh sweet awesome. Thanks so
good to meet everyone. legs. So anyway,